Cool.
Hello, everyone, and welcome
to lecture 4 of CME 295.
So today is Friday,
October, the 17,
which means that the
midterm is one week away.
So before we start,
I'm just going
to go over some logistics
to make sure we're all
aligned on what to expect.
So the midterm will take
place next week same time.
Instead of an hour
and 15 minutes,
it will be an hour
and 30 minutes.
So it's 3:30 to 5:00
in this classroom.
Just like business as usual.
In terms of topics,
the midterm will
be about lectures 1,
2, and 3, which we had,
and this one,
which is lecture 4.
So just to give you
an overview of what
you can expect in
the midterm, there's
going to be some
multi-choice questions along
with some free form
questions, but they're mainly
going to be about the things
that we've seen in class.
So if you watch the recordings,
or attend the lectures,
and just go through the slides,
and know the important formulas,
I think you'll be fine.
So I know that you may have
questions until next week,
so that's why after this
lecture with Shervin,
we will be holding office hours.
So feel free to come to us
and ask us any questions.
And of course, we'll
be fully available
between now and next week.
So in case you
have any questions,
feel free to ping us on Ed.
And yeah, we'll make
sure to respond.
Cool.
I also know that a number of
you are auditing this class.
So in case you're still
interested to take
the midterm for
some reason, maybe
because you have an upcoming
interview, just tell us,
so that we can just expect
the number of copies to print.
So we'll be printing
this on Monday.
So just let us over the weekend
in case you're interested.
Cool.
So that's for the midterm.
And then the second piece
of news is the final.
So we said that we were
working on the dates.
So we finally finalized the
dates which did not change.
So it's Wednesday,
December the 10.
OK.
So a little bit late,
7:00 PM to 8:30 PM.
So it's a slot that we have.
The location is
different from this one.
So it's in this room.
And the final will only
cover the second part
of the class, which is
basically lectures 5 to 9.
Any questions on this?
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Good question.
So is it closed notes?
Yes.
Yeah.
So the question is, what is the
format of the multiple choice?
So you'll have-- so we did
not finish writing the exam,
but it's going to be something
like you have a question
and let's say, you have
three, four possible answers
and then you just
choose the one that.
That's correct.
Something like this.
And you'll also
have some free form,
like you'll have to just
answer in your own words.
Yeah.
Thanks.
So the question is, are we
allowed to take anything?
So it's closed book.
So no.
Yeah.
Nothing.
Just a pen.
Yeah.
Question is no calculator.
You will not need a calculator.
But speaking of
the cheat sheets,
so I'm not sure if we
mentioned, I think we did,
so there is a cheat
sheet for this one,
which we cannot bring to the
exam but you can use just
for your studying
that's on the website.
Class website.
So Jess recommends
looking at it.
Cool.
So super clear for everyone?
Very cool.
Well, OK.
As always, we'll be
starting the class
just recapping what we saw
in the previous lecture.
So if you remember,
we basically studied
a new kind of
architecture, which
was called the mixture
of experts, which is such
that if you have an
input, what you want
is to not necessarily
activate all the parameters.
And so you are in a setting
where you have multiple experts,
and in the forward pass, you
only activate some of them.
So that's a sparse MOE.
You also have the
dense MOE, which
basically weights the
outputs as a function
of the output of the gate.
So we saw that this
architecture was used in LLMs,
and it was mainly used
to be able to scale
this LLMs without
incurring an expensive cost
at inference time,
because you don't want
to activate all the parameters.
The second thing
that we saw was just
defining what an LLM
was and in particular,
how you could decide on what
the next token prediction is.
So we saw three methods.
First one was we
called greedy decoding,
which was always taking
the highest probable token.
The second method we
saw was beam search,
where we kept track of the
K most probable sequences.
And then the third
one was sampling.
So we're not doing
the most probable.
We're not keeping track of the
highest probable sequences.
What we do is we sample
the next token with respect
to the distribution
that we get as outputs.
And then we saw there's
this hyperparameter that's
called temperature
that allows you
to tweak how spiky you want your
distribution to like versus not.
And we also saw some inference
optimization techniques,
which are used in
practice to avoid having
a big cost at decoding time.
So I'm not going to
just mention everything,
but I would say KV
cache, for instance,
is an important method.
So yeah, just
recommend just knowing
what it is along
with the other ones.
And with that, we're
going to start lecture 4.
And actually, I was really
looking forward to today
because lecture 1, we
saw what self-attention
was, what a transformer was.
Second lecture, we
saw some of the tricks
that people use today and
some of the variations
from the transformer.
We introduced what an
LLM was last lecture.
And this lecture,
we're finally going
to see how these
LLMs are trained.
So today, we're going to
focus on LLM training.
And the first thing
that I'm going to say
is if you've been
in the ML field for,
let's say, more than
a few years now, you
may have noticed
that traditionally,
if you had a task,
what you would do
is train a model
specifically for that task.
So let's suppose 10
years ago, let's suppose
we had a task which was
around detecting spam.
You would train a model
specifically to detect spams.
So you would train
on the training set,
eval on the validation set,
and then test on the test set.
If you had another use case,
let's suppose sentiment
extraction, you would train
a model specifically for that
and so on and so forth.
But one could argue
that these tasks,
they are not
completely disjoint.
They're all involving just
understanding the text.
So one could argue
we could find a way
to somehow leverage the
knowledge that we acquired
during training for,
let's say, one task
and reuse that for another task.
So this method has a name.
It's been around for
some time, and it's
called transfer learning.
So the goal of
transfer learning is
to not always start from
scratch if you have a new task.
It's to start with
some pre-trained model,
and we're going to see what
pre-trained is, and then
tune it for your task instead
of starting from scratch.
Well, it's basically
the paradigm
on which LLMs are trained.
So the idea here is
that all these tasks,
they involve
understanding language.
So what we're going to do is
have what we call a pre-training
stage, which involves training
your LLM on vast amounts of data
to just understand
what language,
what code is and then have a
second stage of, quote unquote,
"tuning."
And we're going to see a
little bit what that tuning is.
But in that second
stage, we're going
to take our pre-trained model
and somehow find a way to tune
the weights to adapt
to a specific task.
So as an example, here, we
would pre-train a huge model
and then suppose
for spam detection.
We would somehow tune it for
that sentiment extraction, same.
We would tune it
for that and so on.
So this is just to take
the example from before.
And the idea here is in
order to obtain these models,
we're not going to
start from scratch.
Cool.
So now, we're going to
see what pre-training is.
So pre-training
is by far the most
expensive both in
terms of compute, cost,
everything part of the training.
So what it does is taking
a huge amount of data
and training your LLM to
just predict the next token.
And here, by data, what I
mean is basically everything
you can find.
So it can be text in English.
It can be text in
other languages.
It can be even code, can be
code in different languages,
can be basically
the whole internet.
We're going to see
some of the data sets
that people use for that,
but you can think of this
as just training your model to
try to predict anything that's
written.
And as I mentioned,
the objective here
is to predict the next token.
So if you remember, our
LLM is a text-to-text model
and most likely a decoder
only model in more than 90%
of the cases.
So what it does is it
takes some input text,
and it tries to always
predict the next token
in an iterative basis.
So in terms of the data
sets that are used,
you will see the term Common
Crawl a lot on papers.
It's basically a data
set composed of anything
you can find on the internet.
So I think they have something
like three billion pages
per month.
So if you go on their website,
they have a huge archive.
So there's a bunch
of other websites
as well that you
can find in there.
So for instance, Wikipedia
articles, any social media
as well, like Reddit.
And there are a lot of Reddit
conversations in those data
sets.
You have a lot of codes,
and of course, you
have a bunch of places for that.
You have GitHub, you have Stack
Overflow, all these forums
that talk about codes.
So all of this is
meant for your model
to just understand the structure
of the language and code.
And in terms of size, so
it's measured in terms
of tokens, number of tokens.
And one order of magnitude
that I want you to remember
is on the order of
hundreds of billions
or even trillions or even
tens of trillions of tokens.
So I'll give you an example.
So GPT-3 was trained
on 300 billion tokens.
And for instance,
Llama 3, which was
I believe published
last year, was
trained on 15 trillion tokens.
So these are huge data sets.
So before we go further, I want
to introduce two notations.
And I think one of them I
introduced it last lecture.
The reason why I want to talk
to you about these notations
is they're used everywhere
to talk about how
much compute some model needs.
So the first notation
is FLOPs, which
stands for floating operations.
And what it is it's
a unit of compute.
So the higher the FLOPs, the
more operations are involved.
Because by definition,
FLOPs is the number
of operations that involve
floating point numbers.
So floating point numbers,
you can think of them
as just numbers
with decimal points.
So in terms of order
of magnitudes, training
an LLM is on the order of
10 to the power of 25 FLOPs.
And the way you obtain
FLOPs, so usually, it's
a complicated formula.
But in your mind,
you can think of it
as something that is a function
of the size of your data,
so the number of tokens
that you train it on,
and the number of
parameters of your model.
So there's not an
universal formula
because it also is a
function of the architecture.
So you can think, for instance,
MOE based LLMs as requiring,
let's say, less compute
because only some parts are
activated compared to,
let's say, dense LLMs.
But you can just
think of it as it's
a function of the number
of tokens and parameters.
It's like O of the product
between the two, more or less.
And then there's
a second notation
that I want to introduce,
which is also FLOPS,
but it's different.
So here, FLOPS stands for
floating point operations
per second.
So it's a measure
of compute speeds.
So it's basically how
fast can your hardware
execute these operations.
And so you also have some
order of magnitudes here.
But if you're into,
let's say GPUs,
you will see that in
the description of GPUs,
they always indicate FLOPS.
And we will see
that in a second.
But I just want to call out
that FLOPS here is usually
all caps, although you may
see some papers that use one
for the other,
which is confusing.
So I'll just recommend just
contextualizing this notation
with respect to the sentence
that it is in because sometimes
people actually switch the two.
But this is the common notation.
So far, so good?
Cool.
So now, we know that we
have a pre-training step.
We know it involves
a lot of compute.
a lot of data.
We know our model is large.
So what people did
was trying to see
how the performance evolves
as a function of model size
and training size.
And there is this one
paper called Scaling Loss
for Neural Language Models
that was published in 2020
that performed a
bunch of experiments
by varying these parameters.
And what they found was
the more compute you have,
the better your model learns
about predicting the next token.
Same for data set size.
So the bigger your training
set, the better it is,
and the bigger your
model, the better it is.
So for some time, I think,
between 2019 and 2024,
you were seeing models that
were larger and larger,
just people just
building things that
were bigger and bigger because
according to these experiments,
the performance was
just getting better.
So something else
that they noticed
was bigger models
tend to be more
what they call sample efficient.
So what that means is for
an equal amount of tokens
that is processed,
you will have a better
performance with a bigger model
compared to a smaller one.
But then you can wonder, we
don't have unlimited compute.
Compute is expensive.
It has a lot of drawbacks.
So you have a fixed
compute, and people also
try to answer the question given
a certain amount of compute,
how can you fix your training
set size and your model size
in a way that's more optimal?
Because here, you need to
decide how big is your model.
So what they did is they
fixed a unit of compute, which
is the color of these curves.
And they tried training
models of different sizes
with different
training set size.
And what they saw was that there
was always a sweet spot here,
which followed some kind of
relationship, and in particular,
this is a table that
summarizes, quote unquote,
"the optimal set of number of
parameters and training set
size," which is sometimes
called the Chinchilla law.
And what they realized was if
you have an amount of training
set size that's about
20 times the model size,
then you're spending your
compute in a, quote unquote,
"an optimal way."
And in particular,
GPT-3, for instance, I
think it was like 175
billion parameters,
if I remember
correctly, but it's only
trained on 300 billion tokens.
So this one, for instance,
is, according to this,
"really undertrained,"
quote unquote.
I think there was a question.
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
So yeah.
The question is, do they
fit the neural architecture?
So I think by now,
everyone agrees
that LLMs are transformer-based
decoder only models.
So everyone uses the same model.
So you can assume that
when I say LLM here,
it basically means decoder
only transformer-based models.
[AUDIO OUT]
Yeah.
Question is architecture change
does not play a big role.
So that's what they say
actually in their paper.
They say the thing
that changes the most
is the amount of tokens
on which you train
and the size of your model.
Cool.
Any other questions?
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
Oh, yeah.
Good question.
So question is,
is there some kind
of transfer learning between
different versions of models?
So for a lot of these models,
they're actually closed source.
So they don't exactly
reveal these things.
But I guess it's an
interesting question,
one that I cannot
answer in a general way.
So maybe I think it's the
best answer I can give you.
But in any case, when you
look at some of these papers,
they always state how much
it costs to train this.
And it's always in
the order of millions.
It's always an expensive
step regardless.
Cool.
Just speaking of
that, so pre-training
has a lot of challenges.
One of them is cost.
So when I say, millions
of dollars, it's minimum.
I think it can even cost
tens of millions of dollars
or sometimes hundreds
of millions of dollars.
It takes a lot of
time, and people
have been mindful of the
impact on the environment.
So they've also been including
the ecological costs.
So the other challenge is
that the pre-training step
is on data that is up to the
time at which you pre-train
your model on.
So what that means is that
the knowledge that you acquire
from training on this
data set can only
go up until the date at
which you cut your data set.
So this date is called
the knowledge cutoff date.
And so what that means
is your base model,
your pre-trained
base model has no way
to know by itself knowledge
that occurred after this date.
And speaking of that,
a lot of papers,
they have tried to edit
knowledge, inject knowledge.
It's always tricky because
there's not a clean way
to change the
weights in a way that
does not penalize some parts.
So I guess what
people want to do
is inject knowledge but not
regress in some other domains.
And this is a very hard problem.
And of course,
these models, they
try to predict the next token.
And there's this
question of what
if it just generates
something that it
has seen at training time?
So what we call plagiarism.
So there's always a risk.
So these are all the
challenges I just
want to illustrate when I
said knowledge cutoff date.
So if you go on, let's say,
the OpenAI website or Google
website to look at the model
cards, you will always see--
so I'm not sure as
you can see from here,
but there is always a line on
knowledge cutoff date, which
tells you on when the
pre-training of this model
was done.
So here, for instance, GPT-5
was released a few weeks ago,
and here, it says, the knowledge
cutoff date is September 30.
So you can guess that they've
done their pre-training
around that stage.
Cool.
Any questions on the first part?
All good?
Perfect.
So in this first
part, we've seen
that pre-training was a crucial
step of the LLM training
process.
And we've seen all
these big numbers.
And one could wonder, well, how
can you train such a big model
on such a big amount of data?
How do people do that?
So this is what we're
going to see here.
So this is what I mentioned.
So LLMs, you can think
of them as decoder only
transformer-based models.
So in order to train your
model, you need that.
You need a lot of
data, but then if you
look at your architecture, you
see that a lot of the operations
involve matrix multiplications.
And I guess I have
a question for you.
What is the kind
of hardware that
loves matrix multiplications?
GPUs.
Yes.
So you also need GPUs.
Actually more than one.
Yeah.
You had a question.
[AUDIO OUT]
Oh.
Question is GPT for inference.
So this one, we're going
to focus on training,
but requirements for GPUs,
they differ a little bit
between training and
inference, but in this part,
we're solely
focused on training.
And speaking of GPUs, I guess,
it's not GPUs everywhere
because, for instance,
Google, they've
developed their own
hardware that's called TPUs,
but any non Google-based
models, they've most likely
been trained on GPUs.
Cool.
So in order to train your
model, what do you do?
So first of all,
you have your LLM
which is now-- so
it is this model,
but now, we're representing
with a box just for simplicity.
You initialize it.
It's a lot of parameters.
So you can think of the scale as
being somewhere around billions
to hundreds of billions of
parameters, so huge model.
And what are the steps
involved to train a model?
Well, what you're trying to
do is to tune the weights,
so that the model can learn
how to generate the next token.
So you have one step called
the forward pass, where
you have a bunch of
data that you're trying
to pass through the network.
And while we do
that, I just want
to call out things that are
important to note that we
need to somehow save in memory.
So when you do
this forward pass,
you have something that's called
activations, which are basically
the values at each layer that
are needed in order to compute
the loss.
So the loss tells
you how off you
are compared to the label that
you want to train this on.
And so the amount of memory
that you will use here
is dependent on a lot of things.
It's dependent on the
model size, which impacts
the number of activations.
It's dependent on how big your
batch of data is for training.
And it's dependent on how
large your context length is,
because if you remember, here we
have O of N squared complexity
because of this
self-attention operation,
where N is the sequence length.
So you have all these
parameters that come into play.
So once you do the
forward pass, let's
suppose you compute the loss.
You know how off you are
compared to your label.
Now, the next step
is to somehow tweak
the weights in a way
that minimizes the loss.
So how do you do that?
There is this another pass
called backwards pass.
So what this pass does
is quantify the direction
where the loss is
going to be minimized.
It's called the gradient.
You take the gradient
of the loss with respect
to each parameter.
Well, gradients, they also need
to be saved somewhere in memory.
And then you have finally
the weights update,
which is where you know where
the direction at which your loss
is going to be minimized.
So you apply that
update to your weights.
And you typically use
optimizers out there.
Have you heard of
Adam optimizer?
Yeah.
So Adam optimizer is
just a fancy version
that has some additional
quantities, which
keep track of--
which are basically a
function of the gradients.
So you have the first moment
and the second moment,
which is basically the moving
average of the gradient
and the squared gradients.
And all these quantities,
so the first moment,
the second moment, you also
need to somehow save them
somewhere in memory.
So it's a lot of things to save.
Well, OK.
Breaking news, memory
is not unlimited.
Memory is limited.
And so here, what we
have in front of us
is the description of a GPU.
I think.
Yeah.
H100, which is a very good GPU.
And you will see in
that description,
there's a line on GPU memory.
So GPU memory is your
amount of memory per GPU.
It's 80 gig for this one.
It's quite large.
So it's in on the order
of tens of gigabytes.
So you need to store all these
things in 80 gigabytes, which
is not a lot.
So what are we doing?
What will you be doing?
So I guess the
idea is to leverage
not one but several GPUs in
order to somehow distribute
the load across CPUs.
And in order to do that,
you have several methods,
which we will see in a second.
So the first set of methods
is called data parallelism,
also known as DP.
So what this set
of methods does is
it distributes data across
GPUs, so that this forward
pass and backward pass, they
can all be done independently.
And so the idea here is to
divide the batch of data
across devices, and then in
order to do that, of course,
you need to have a copy
of the model per device.
Because of course, you need
to compute the activations.
You need to compute
all these things.
But when you do that, you're are
able to reduce the memory that
is linked to the batch size.
So that's called
data parallelism.
Yes.
Question is how about
the gradient update?
Well, it's a great question.
So what do you do when you have
independent computations here
and there?
Well, the gradient
is just the average
of the gradients for this thing.
So you have some communication
in between the GPUs
that basically aggregates
the gradient for the updates.
So I have a question for you.
Is this the answer
to everything?
If we just scale
up like this for,
I don't know, a lot of GPUs,
is it great, always great
or do we have cons?
Oh, yeah.
Great point.
So yeah, you have
to fit one model.
So yeah, this is a great point.
So the second point
that I will add
is you have an
additional cost, which
is called communication
cost, because you
need to somehow communicate
between your GPUs
in order to aggregate
some quantities.
So your training is
going to be slower.
It's good.
You can scale up the memory.
Of course, you need to
fit a model on a device,
and we will see
how we to do that.
But you will be incurring
those communication costs,
so it's not all great.
So speaking of the
memory and the fact
that we want to, I guess,
be able to at least
store a model per device.
So people have realized
that there's actually
a lot of duplication.
And there has been
a paper on wanting
to deduplicate this
duplicate information
and this method is called ZeRO,
ZeRO redundancy optimization.
And the idea is
that on each GPU,
you store the same parameters,
you store the same gradients,
you store the same
optimizer states.
So the idea here is how
about we shard, we partition
those quantities across GPUs?
So the first variation is around
sharing the optimizer state.
So meaning, we partition
those states across the GPUs.
So this reduces the
memory by a lot.
We can also partition
the gradients,
and we can also
partition the parameters.
So here, we have no
redundant information.
Things are just partitioned.
Well, the problem
is you're going
to have even more
communication costs,
but at least it allows for
us to decrease the memory
load on each GPU.
So this is ZeRO, so there's
ZeRO 1, ZeRO 2, ZeRO 3.
And I guess the
variation that you
will choose will be a function
of how sensitive you are to,
I guess, training time
and how big is your model
and whether this will
be an actual problem,
or are you just fine with
just storing everything?
So that's one set of methods.
So this set of methods is,
again, data parallelism.
So it's basically you having
independent sets of data that
are handled by different GPUs.
Well, you have another
set of methods that's
called model parallelism.
So model parallelism tries to
parallelize the operation even
within one batch.
So there's a bunch of methods.
I don't want to sound
too like a catalog.
So we're not going through
them all but one by one.
But I will just call out a
few that are worth noting.
So if you remember last lecture,
we talked about MOE-based LLMs
and how sequences were being
sent to different experts.
Well, there is a way
to distribute that
across GPUs via this expert
parallelism techniques, which
is having, let's say, one
expert on a device, another one
on another device.
So that's one
thing worth noting.
Another one, I will say,
so a tensor parallelism
is when you have big matrix
multiplications to somehow cut
that in a way that decreases
the memory required for that.
And maybe the last one I will
say is pipeline parallelism.
It's when you consider
a forward pass
as involving several layers.
So you're going to say that
one GPU is going to only
be responsible for, let's
say, layers 1 to 3 and then
another one layer 3--
sorry, 4 to 5, 4, 5, 6,
and so on and so forth.
So you also have that
kind of parallelism.
But anyways, there's
a bunch of techniques.
And the ones that
I mentioned they
fall in the bucket
of model parallelism.
Make sense?
No need to know the
details on there.
But I think just knowing that
there are several methods
and just a rough idea, I think,
is a good thing to have in mind.
Cool.
So what did we do?
So we realized that during
the training process,
we had to save a lot
of things in memory.
So what we saw was
techniques that
reduce the burden of
having memory per GPU,
so we are trying to
distribute that across GPUs.
So we saw data
parallelism and then
the ZeRO method that has
some extra optimizations.
And we saw model
parallelism as well.
So now, we're going to see
another technique that leverages
the structure of the GPU.
And you may have heard
of this technique.
It's called flash attention.
It was actually developed
here at Stanford in 2022.
And in order for me to talk
to you about this technique,
I want to tell you more about
what the GPU is composed of.
So if you look under the hood--
well, GPU is very complicated
and I'm for sure not--
I don't know everything either.
But what I know is that we have
two kinds of memories in GPU.
So you have one kind of memory
that's big but relatively slow.
That's in the HBM.
And then another kind of
memory that is fast but much,
much smaller, which is
on chip next to where
the compute happens.
That's called the SRAM.
So you have HBM and SRAM.
HBM has something around
tens of gigabytes.
So it's like the GPU memory
that you saw in the description.
SRAM is much smaller.
It's like something around
several tens of megabytes
let's say.
So it's much smaller, but
then it is 10 times faster.
So this one is a few terabytes
per second let's say.
And the SRAM is tens of
terabytes per second.
So it's a noticeable
difference in speed.
So what we want is
to somehow leverage
the strength of these
kinds of memories
in order to speed
up the attention
computation in an exact way.
So what do I mean by exact way?
So what I mean is we're not
making any approximations
to the computation.
What we're doing is
we're just leveraging
the strength of these components
and sending the computation
in a clever way.
So if you remember, the
self-attention computation
is done with this very
important formula.
So it's softmax of
queries and keys
over some scaling
factor times V.
So this allows queries to
interact with everyone else.
So in matrix form, you
can think of queries
as having the number of rows
equal to the sequence length.
And then columns to being
the dimension of the query.
And then same for key and value.
So you have this big
matrix multiplications.
So if you do it--
if you do this
computation, the standards
the vanilla way,
what you would do
is store them in the
big but slow memory
component of the GPU.
So you would store
it in the HBM.
So here is what you
would do if you were
to not do any optimization.
So you would take those matrices
from the big but slow HBM,
perform the computation, and
then write it back to the HBM.
And then you would read that
result again from the HBM,
compute the softmax, and then
write it back to the HBM.
And then you would again load
this plus the value matrix,
multiply them, and then
write them to the HBM.
See, there's a lot read
and write to the HBM.
So it's a lot of data
transfer, which actually
becomes the bottleneck.
So a GPU is very, very fast,
but then you spend a lot of time
just loading your
matrices from the memory.
The reason why you do that
is because of this softmax
operation.
So do you remember
what a softmax does?
So it normalizes the quantities,
so that they sum to 1.
But it's row dependent
meaning that each row needs
to sum up to 1.
So in a sense, you need that
computation to happen first
before you do your softmax.
If you just look
at it like that,
you would think, yeah, you need
to do the whole thing first.
Well, it turns
out that you don't
need to do everything at once.
And this is the core idea
behind flash attention.
So what flash
attention does is it
tries to minimize
the amount of read
and write from and to the HBM
and instead takes small blocks--
and it's called tiling, the
method is called tiling.
It takes small blocks
that it sends to the SRAM,
so that it gets
computed from end
to end before being
sent back to the HBM.
Does that make sense?
So the idea is let's send
small matrices into the SRAM,
so that it does the whole
full end-to-end computation
and just send it
back to the HBM,
because we want to
minimize the amount read
and write from the HBM.
So here is how you would do it.
So you remember, the
softmax computation
with the query and the
key and then the value.
Well, what you would do
is to cut your matrices
and then proceed step by step.
But then there's a
cool trick that I
want to talk to
you about, which is
that you don't need to
compute the whole matrix
inside a softmax in order
to achieve the whole softmax
computation.
Because if you think
about it, let's suppose
you have a whole matrix,
and then you have different,
let's say, columns or
submatrices, S1 to SN,
well, softmax of
this huge matrix
is equal to this matrix,
where the softmax is taken
with respect to each
of these submatrices
up to some scaling factor.
So this is the core trick.
And if you want to
be convinced of it,
just look at the
softmax formula,
it's exponential of something
over some quantity, which
is shared across the row.
So this scaling factor will just
fix this with respect to that.
So with this in
mind, what we will do
is take each respective
slices of this matrices,
do the whole computation,
and then populate
the corresponding entry
in the output matrix.
So we will do that
between, let's say,
the first slice of the
query and the first slice
of the keys and the values.
And then we will repeat for
the other slice until the end.
And then we will repeat
for the other queries
as well until the end.
So what the paper explains
is how this scaling factor
is being computed.
So this one is some formula
that I did not put on the slide,
so it's not necessary for
you to memorize the formula.
It's just the idea.
And the idea is
exactly this trick.
So once you do that,
you basically end up
with only one read from the HPM.
And these [INAUDIBLE] quantities
are stored in the SRAM.
And then they're read
from the SRAM, which
is very fast, and then computed,
and then back to the SRAM.
And then at the end, in order
to accumulate the results,
they're being sent
back to the HBM.
So just to make
sure we're clear.
So in green, it's basically
when it's read from SRAM,
and then in blue,
it's from the HBM.
You have a question?
Yeah.
[AUDIO OUT]
The question is, do you take the
whole row or a portion of it?
So you can take a portion of it.
But just for
illustrative purposes,
here we take the exclusive.
This is just for
illustrative purposes.
You can think of your matrix
as being completely a grid.
And then you just
multiply accordingly.
But yeah, this is just
for illustrative purposes.
Yeah.
So the question is,
are you computing alpha
and all these
quantities on the fly
or do you have some estimation?
So all of this is
exact, and they're
computed in an iterative basis.
So the way it works is when
you populate the output,
you will keep on having
some extra quantity that
will adjust for that.
Think of it as just
some formula that works.
So yeah, I highly recommend
looking at the paper.
They actually explicit
that quite a lot.
So the paper is
Flash Attention, fast
and memory efficient exact
attention with IO awareness.
All of the links
are in the slides.
But yeah, I highly
recommend just
looking at the exact formula in
case you want to be convinced.
Cool.
But the idea makes
sense overall?
Any questions on this?
Cool.
Well, this was flash
attention, but there's actually
another idea from the paper.
So this was only the
first idea, which
was around making the
attention computation faster.
The second idea is given that
the attention computation is
faster, now let's
try to be smarter
about the backwards pass,
because when you compute
in the backwards
pass, when you compute
the gradient of the loss
with respect to a parameter,
the chain rule will surface
some activations that you
need to have in memory.
Well, here, given that computing
these activations is very fast,
one idea is to just
not store activations
from the forward pass or at
least not store everything,
but instead in the
backwards pass,
compute these activations again.
So it's called
the recomputation.
So when you do the forward
pass, you compute an activation
to be able to compute
the loss, but then
instead of saving it to reuse
it during the gradient update,
you will just
discard it and then
recompute the activation
during the backwards pass
with this very fast technique.
And when you do that, it's
actually quite remarkable.
So you do more operations.
So gigaFLOPs is just
a derivative of FLOPs.
So it's the number of
operations you're doing.
So with flash attention,
you're doing more operations
because you're actually
recomputing things.
But then so you also see fewer
read and writes from the HBM.
So here, for instance, it
was 40.3 in the standard way
and then 4 point-- so it's
like almost a 10x reduction.
But then you see that the
runtime is also smaller.
So this is very remarkable
because usually,
when you recompute things,
you are saving memory
but at the expense of runtime.
You're just taking longer.
But here, you're not only
taking less amount of time,
you're also saving memory.
So you're basically
having everything.
It's the best of all worlds.
So this is what flash
attention mentioned.
So you will see that there
are some other, I guess,
variants of flash attention.
So flash attention
2, flash attention 3.
And I would say that these are
more adaptation of these methods
to the current infra,
because each new GPU comes
with new pros and cons, so
strengths and weaknesses.
And I guess there's
always a way to make
these optimizations better.
But yeah, I would say
flash attention is
quite a common trick, and I
think it's a very good thing to.
So does that make sense?
Cool.
I'll take that as a yes.
OK.
Cool.
OK, so last thing--
no, we have a few things that
I want to talk to you about.
So you have your LLM
with a bunch of weights.
These weights are
all floating points.
So you can think of
them as just being
numbers with a bunch of
numbers after the decimal.
One natural question
you can ask yourself
is, do you really need to
know that much precision
after the decimal point to
be able to do a good job?
I guess put another
way, can you just
cut your precision in
some way to save on memory
but then keep the
same performance?
So this is the idea
behind quantization.
So quantization is the
process of converting
the precision of a
number from, let's say,
one setting to another.
In order to better
understand that,
I think it's important to
know how floating points--
sorry, floating point
numbers, how they are encoded.
So in practice, they're
just a bunch of bits.
And here, you have some bits
that are responsible for,
let's say, the
exponent, some that
are responsible for the
mantissa, which is basically
how granular your number is.
And then one that
is about the sign.
So you have a bunch of
representations of floats.
So the most common
ones are in this table.
So you have so single point
precision, half precision,
floating point
64, brain float 16
that are each having different
granularities for the three
dimensions.
So if we take the
first two rows, which
are the two most common
representations that you will
see out there, floating point 16
is only represented on 16 bits
compared to 32.
So it takes basically
half the memory
if you want to think
about it this way.
But then it's less precise,
meaning it's less granular.
So I guess one
idea that we could
have is to somehow decrease the
granularity of these weights
and these numbers, hoping that
it will not impact performance
too much.
So another thing that
I want to mention
is back to that GPU description.
You see that there is also
a bunch of information
around the compute speed.
So I'm not sure if you can
see very well on there.
Can you see very
well on the slide?
So I'll read it.
The compute speed as a function
of which representation
you're using.
So here, if you're
using FP64, which
is this super granular way
of representing numbers,
you only have 34 teraFLOPs
of compute speed.
But then if you're
using a, let's say,
FP32, which is half of it, you
can double your compute speed
and so on.
You have all these
other numbers as well.
So the idea is you
can save on memory.
You can also go faster.
So with this in
mind, I just want
to touch on one last
technique before giving it
to Shervin, which is
mixed precision training.
So the idea behind
mixed precision training
is to leverage different
granularities of float
representations such
that it will not
hurt the performance too much
but allow you to save on memory
and do things faster.
So the idea behind
mixed precision training
is you have your models or
you have your model, you
keep your weights in
high precision, so FP32,
and all the
operations that you do
in the forward
and backward pass,
you're going to do it
in a lower precision.
So in this case, FP16.
But then the weight updates
will be done still in FP32.
So the authors of the
paper, when they did that,
basically what they
realized was the performance
was not degraded too much.
But then you had a lot
of savings on memory
and then it was running faster.
So now you may wonder, well,
why are you keeping the weights
at a high precision but not
the activations and so on?
So I can offer you just
a bit of intuition.
So whenever you
perform a forward pass,
you're performing
that on a set of data.
But that set of data
can be noisy in itself.
So maybe all the
decimal points after--
so all the numbers
after the decimal point
may not be as useful.
So you can think of this update
as being more in which direction
should the weights go
to a more optimal state.
So it doesn't require
them to be super precise,
but then it's much more
important to keep your weights,
so the weights of the model
in high precision in order
to not accumulate errors
due to quantization.
That's one way just
think about it.
But the long story
short is if you
reduce the granularity
of some numbers,
then you will have
a lot of benefits
and not a lot of disadvantages
in terms of the performance.
Cool.
Yeah.
That's a great question.
So the question is, do
you apply this technique
to all weights of all layers
or just to some of them?
So there has been a
lot of papers on that.
And the answer is there
are some variations to it.
And so the answer
is not necessarily.
So I do have some pointers.
Happy to share them with you.
But some parts may be more
important than others.
So this strategy is a little
bit a high level idea,
but there are always some
variations from setup to setup.
Yeah.
So is your question that
people rely on the relationship
between compute--
and sorry, not compute,
parameters and token
from the Chinchilla
paper, but it
may be different from
their setup which
may introduce something-- this
is basically your question?
So the question
is, is there also
an optimal precision to use?
So I would say, people
use different things.
There's not like a set way
where everyone does something.
But I would say that these
scaling, like this Chinchilla
law, is actually something
that some authors,
they try to reproduce
for their own model.
So actually, for instance,
the Llama 3 paper,
there's a whole
part around trying
to have some relationship
between given
a fixed amount of compute, what
is the optimal number of tokens
and then a number of parameters
that is unique to their setup.
So what people do is they
do this thing themselves
on a small amount of training
set and on smaller models,
so that it doesn't
cost them too much.
They try to see what the
relationship is for their setup,
and then they extrapolate.
And I believe
that's how Llama 3--
so I think there's
a model that--
so Llama 3, 405
billion parameters.
I think they had the whole
section just justifying
that they came up to this
number with some experiments
that they run.
So to your question,
I think it highly
depends on the kind of model
that someone is training.
And they'll probably
have this analysis,
I guess, with respect
to their own setup.
Does that answer your question?
Cool.
OK.
Great.
Yeah.
The question is,
is there something
you can do about the range?
So there are several
types of quantization.
We're not going
into details here,
but I can give you a ZeRO
point quantization and absmax
quantization, which are
different techniques that
play with these ranges.
There's also
quantization technique
that Shervin will cover
that also talks about that.
So yeah, stay tuned for this.
But I think ZeRO point
quantization and absmax are
ones that maybe you
can look into for this.
Cool.
So with that, I'm going
to give it to Shervin.
Thank you, Afshin.
So now, we have seen how
a pre-training worked.
We're going to see together
the next stages of training.
So as we saw with
Afshin, pre-training
was a way to build the intuition
to the model about how language
was constructed and about the
main characteristics of what is
contained in the training data.
That is general enough.
So this is why we had corpuses
that spans huge corpora of texts
that are typically
of the size of what
you find on the internet.
So typically, very large
and raw and conveying
aspects of language.
So now, you might
want to ask yourself,
how can we make such
knowledge actually helpful?
So this is something
that we're going
to discuss just in a second.
But before we discuss about what
could motivate further training,
I want to come back to some very
simple example that will surface
what could be such a need.
So let's take our favorite
example about our teddy bear.
And let's say, we have a
very practical use case.
So we have thoroughly
loved our teddy bear.
But now, it has become a bit
dirty, so we need to wash it.
And you might want to ask your
favorite LLM if you can put it
in the washer.
So with the description
that Afshin mentioned
of LLM pre-training,
I wanted to ask
you all what was your
opinion about what
could the output to this be.
So any guesses?
Yep.
Yeah.
Excellent.
So the answer, the guess
was maybe another question.
So I think that is a great guess
that could definitely be it.
So here, in the example,
we put some other sentence
that could be likely,
but the gist is the same.
It has been trained on
next token prediction,
not being an assistant or
someone that is helpful to you.
So this is why it
will try to mimic
what could be the pattern
here and what could
be potential likely next words.
So for example, the
example we put here
is something that relates to how
the teddy bear is composed of.
And because it's in the
same domain as teddy bear
and then when you talk
about washer, then
maybe it has been trained
on data that includes
materials of teddy bears.
So that could be it.
And I have a question
with you all.
Are you happy with it?
No.
Yeah.
Exactly.
So this is why
we're going to see
what we can do with the model
to make it helpful to you.
And this stage is
called fine tuning.
So we're going to see
that it enables us to,
in the general
case of LLMs, make
the LLM a helpful
assistance, but also,
if you have a
specific use case, you
can also use this
technique to tune
the general representation
of the language
towards your task of interest.
But we're going to
focus first on what
is done for LLMs in general.
So first, I want to
define some terms.
So model fine tuning is
commonly known as SFT.
SFT is short for
supervised fine tuning.
So the supervised part suggests
that we need some labels.
And it's actually the case.
So it's pairs of
inputs and outputs
that we provide the
model to be trained on.
And this is why it's
called supervised.
And then fine tuning
is the term that
refers to refining the weights
that have been already trained.
So you start from the
pre-trained weights,
and you further train the
model on additional data
to get a fine tuned model.
And then one interesting
note that I will tell you all
is that the objective function,
even though it's the same,
will differ a bit from
the pre-training task.
So in the pre-training task,
you start with the BOS token,
beginning of
sentence, and you fit
all your corpora of data trying
to predict the next token.
But here, since we have this
supervised fine tuning setup,
where you want the model to
do something useful in cases
of interest, so let's
say, when I ask the model
about washing my teddy bear,
so washing my teddy bear
is actually an input
that I give to the model.
It's fixed.
I don't want the model
to parrot what I say.
I want the model to be
a helpful assistance
to what I conditioned it on.
So in this setup, the
input is not a location
where you would
predict the next token.
You would not do
teacher forcing on it
but rather start from this
input and then predict
the next token onwards.
And then you're
going to tune what
the optimal distribution
of next token
can be based on this input.
So any questions on
the overall idea of SFT
before we dive in a bit deeper?
Yep.
So the question is we don't
put a loss over the input.
That's right.
So you start from the
input, and you start
predicting the next token.
And then the loss calculation
starts from there.
Everything good?
OK.
So what I was just
telling you is
that SFT can be done to tune
your own task of interest,
but also, it's
something that is being
done at one of the main
stages of training LLMs
as you use it every day.
And then this transition
from the model
being a good representation of
language to a useful assistance
is a subcategory of SFT
called instruction tuning.
So instruction tuning
comes from the fact
that we want the model
to answer instructions.
So now, I'm going to
show with the graph what
I was just mentioning regarding
predicting the next word.
So actually, just in a bit.
First, we're going
to look at the data.
So with Afshin, we saw
that the composition
of the data for
pre-training was basically
the whole internet where you
had sources that were carrying
knowledge such as Wikipedia.
And in general, masses
of text of English
that tells the model about how
English and other languages
work, as well as coding.
And here, it's
slightly different.
For instruction
tuning, we're going
to look at data that's
presents to the model
how it can most helpfully
respond to instructions.
So you can divide this
in several categories.
So here, we present
some categories
that could be helpful
to users of LLMs.
For example, story writing.
You're interested
in writing a story.
You give it a set
of instructions,
and then you have a ground
truth that is attached to it.
Other examples include a poem
creation, list generation,
explanation, and many
more that are part
of the data mixture of SFT.
So basically, you run all these
supervised fine tuning training
with the inputs that is given,
and then you train the model
on predicting the output.
And I'm going now to
show what it looks like.
So let's say your
instruction is here.
So you ask your model
to do something.
So it could be formulated
in a different way
but just to keep it
short, I just said, do X.
And then the yellow
part is where
you start fitting your
objective function on.
Does this make sense?
Great.
So as I was mentioning,
the data mixture
includes instruction
geared data.
So for example, you had
all of these kinds of tasks
that users might ask
for at inference time.
So it's what I put under the
category assistant dialogues.
And these days, since you have
all these large models that
already exist out
there, and let's say
you want to generate a new
one, you don't necessarily
have to start from scratch.
So all of these that I mentioned
were originally human written.
So you had all
these instructions
that people gathered, and
you had expert linguists that
had set of instructions on how
to write the best answer that
was fluent, helpful,
and everything
that was geared
towards maximizing
your happiness as a user.
But these days, you can use
these already trained LLMs
to generate such data.
So typically, when you
have a large model that
is very performant, you can feed
it such instructions, sample
some generated outputs, and then
have a human or some other LLM
review the quality.
So it's something
that speeds up a bit
the curation of such data sets.
So I just wanted to
emphasize on the fact
that it's not only human
generated these days,
but you can have
some assistance.
And besides all
of the categories
that you care about,
so typically, math
or how you write a proof,
how things follow each other,
or codes, high
quality code bases,
you also have other aspects
that are very important which
when you release a product like
this to the wider population
that come under the
umbrella of safety.
So you want your model to be
helpful but also harmless.
So you also have
in the data mixture
oftentimes a subset that
enforces the model's behavior
not to repeat some of
the harmful content it
might have seen on its
pre-training corpus.
So it will include
techniques that
might reject some user prompts.
So you might have tested on your
own the limits of an LLM today.
If you submit queries that
might lead to something that is
considered bad, it would
just say, OK, sorry,
I cannot answer this.
And this sorry, I cannot answer
could be done via regex but very
rarely because
it's not scalable.
And people actually embed this
property as part of the model.
So you have techniques that
rejects user queries that
are seen as harmful.
Or there is some
other phenomenon
such as hedging that nuance
the output of the model
in order to not make
blanket statement as well.
So you might have data sets
that includes such flavors.
And you can have
many more depending
on the task of interest
that you're dealing with.
But what I'm listing here is
what usually the LLMs out there
that aim at being general
assistance gather.
They tend to be like general
tasks that are being trained on.
Any questions on the data?
Yep.
So the question is the
story writing example
doesn't precise
what kind of poetry
the story should be about.
So it might be ambiguous.
How can it generalize?
So that is a great point.
So we rely on the
model's knowledge
that it has accumulated
at pre-training time
to be able to generalize
beyond the examples
that it has been fed.
So let's say, now, you
have a story about poetry,
and from pre-training, it
knows about all kinds of poetry
that exist out there.
So you could imagine, after
fitting such an example at
supervised fine tuning time,
that you could give more details
to this prompt.
And then the model
has the ability
to generalize the generation
of the story with respect
to those other attributes.
So you can have--
I think, the example
that you mentioned
is a great example of the
magical ability of LLMs
to adapt to natural language.
And all of that has to do
with the kind of distribution
it has seen in the past
and what we teach it.
So I think the concept
itself of writing stories
is the key learning to the model
that it can then generalize.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
OK.
Great.
I think there was
another question here.
Yeah.
So the question is about
the term of alignment.
Is this post training what
is called as being aligned?
So you are ahead of me.
In a few slides, we're
going to talk about it.
Great questions.
Any other question?
Awesome.
So and then just like Afshin did
it for the pre-training part,
I'm going to give some
orders of magnitude.
So the same GPT-3
and Llama 3 papers
that Afshin referred
some numbers from
don't actually give
their statistics
in terms of token numbers for
the instruction tuning side
but actually in
number of examples.
So you see you have about 13
K used GPT-3 and 10 million
for Llama 3.
And OK.
So let's do some
quick estimation.
Let's say each example
is about 1,000 tokens.
When you multiply that with
the number of examples,
you see that the size of
the data sets used for SFT
is several orders of magnitude
lower than the one used
for pre-training.
So the mental model that
you need to have here
is that pre-training
is a lot of data
you want to learn about general
characteristics, about language.
And then SFT is
more exactly what--
so someone was
mentioning just now
regarding alignments-- was
aligning the goal of the model
to being suited for your tasks.
So typically, very
high quality data
sets and much more concise and
precise in terms of number.
So less order of magnitude.
OK.
Great.
So now, let's try
this exercise again.
What do you think could be the
answer to our instruction tuned
now model to the same question?
Anyone wants to take a guess?
You want to try again.
Yeah.
So the answer was yes.
You can put in the teddy
bear in the washer,
except that you shouldn't put
your teddy bear in the washer.
You should handwash it.
So it will give you the answer
that is helpful to the user.
And indeed, this time
respond to the query.
So which is pretty nice.
So now, we talked
about all the things
that are great about
supervised fine tuning.
Now, I'm going to detail
a bit more about what
could make it hard
or challenging
and then motivate the
optimization part that we're
going to see afterwards.
So first, we talked
about it a bit.
When we have these
data sets, these data
mixtures for SFT training,
we need high quality data.
And when you say
high quality data,
means oftentimes human
involved in the loop,
you need to make sure it abides
with all the rules and all
the characteristics that
the user will care about.
So typically, it's
highly involved.
So originally,
these first models,
they were almost all human.
But now, you might have some
mixture of human and generation.
But one good thing
about these things
is that the data sets they
are trained on are reused.
So it's a work that you do
once, and you can complement
with respect to time.
But it's still very expensive
in time and resources.
So the second point I want to
mention comes back to a point
that someone just made regarding
the distribution of your SFT
data sets and how it would
align with actual inference
distribution.
So in the case of
the story regarding
a specific kind of
poetry, the distribution
of prompts, that precise
the kind of poetry
seems close enough for
generalization to be made.
But you could think about
examples that widely differ.
So let's say you ask for a story
that is in some movie plots,
and it differs from the stories
that you might see in textbooks.
So this could be slightly
out of distribution,
and it could have trouble
generalizing to that.
So prompt distribution
is very important.
And aligning that prompt
distribution with respect
to the target task
is of interest.
Yep.
Yeah.
Great point.
So the question is
about, let's say,
you have SFT tuned your model,
and now, you put a training
input back to the model.
Will you get the same story?
So it has to do
with the phenomenon
that Afshin was mentioning
regarding memorization.
So in practice, you will not
see the same story most likely
because the sampling
that you're doing
is with a non ZeRO temperature.
It will maybe have the same
flavor but not word for word.
Then the flavor of
that story, if you
have the exact same
prompts, might be the same.
It depends on what it has
seen at pre-training time.
But yeah, so the
answer is that if I
had to give a guess on
that precise example,
it might be the same flavor but
definitely not the same wording.
Yeah.
So and it might be
a different story
if the sampling goes through
some other region of the space.
Stories are highly creative
and pre-training corpora
of data mixture had all
kinds of stories in there.
So the specific
example of story is
likely to generate
different outcomes.
Yep.
So the question is, will how
much the model wanders around
depend on the
temperature parameter?
And yes.
So typically, when you have a
higher temperature, you also--
so it's also called
more creative.
And it's for that reason.
It might also
generate things that
are less likely in its output
distribution with respect
to what it has learned.
And this is exactly a case
of something that we learn.
So the answer is yes.
So the question is, is
there any way to tune that?
So when you tune
the temperature,
you exactly do that.
Or were you thinking
about something else?
Yeah.
So the question is, is
there something else
you could do to have
variations in the response?
So for that, I have a
simple but hard solution.
You will need more data
in that category that
will ground the model into
seeing what kind of distribution
we target with such queries.
And I think that will
be one way for the model
to generalize more.
So I think it will be
working on the data part.
Was there another question?
All good.
So yeah.
So this is a very
relevant question
because it touches on the
topic of generalization.
So yeah.
So data mixture matters a lot.
And having points
that are sparse enough
in the distribution
space to give
the gist to the model of
what it needs to learn,
rather than repeating the
same story again and again,
will have a lot to do with
generalization powers.
And then this is something we
are going to see in a second,
how do you evaluate such models?
The feeling that you get
as a user on how helpful
a model tends to be subjective.
So how can you put some
number on it is going
to be a key topic of interest.
And then also very
soon, we're going
to see how to make the
computations not that expensive.
So Afshin talked about training
optimization techniques.
But now, when we're at
the fine tuning stage,
maybe we can go one
step further and see
what simplification
assumption we could make.
OK.
Awesome.
Now, let's dive into
one of these challenges,
which was the evaluation part.
So people have decomposed what
they care about in categories.
So I'm listing here
some dimensions
that are evaluated
against and that
gives some quantitative number.
So you have a general
language where
this benchmark that is
popular is generally one score
that people reports.
It's a MMLU, which
massive multitask
language understanding.
So it has, I think, 50
or so tasks in there
where the model is
being evaluated against,
and you have some score
that you can compare with.
You have benchmarks
on reasoning,
on math reasoning, as
well as code generation.
So here, you have all
sorts of acronyms,
and there is even way more.
So basically, the
setting up benchmark
has been one area of research.
So you always see more
and more benchmark
coming in because people tend to
optimize for those that exist.
And then there are
some gaps that might
be filled by further ones.
And the GSM 8K stands
for grad school--
so yeah, grad school math.
8K stands for the
number of examples.
Yeah, I think so.
Or maybe G stands
for something else,
but it's high school
topics basically.
And one very interesting
pattern that people
have seen as these
models came out
and as they were evaluated
against these benchmarks
is that sometimes for
the same kind of model,
you see all of a sudden a
spike in numbers with respect
to some of these benchmarks
without a clear explanation
behind it.
And there is this
paper that I highly
recommend taking a
look, which explores
the phenomenon of training on
the test task, not the test set.
The test task.
So when you have benchmarks
regarding math reasoning,
let's say, it matters
a lot if the model has
been trained on a
data that relates
to that kind of
reasoning versus not.
And this is why when you type
in those kinds of benchmarks,
you will see that there are sets
of so-called auxiliary training
that can be used
for the model to be
trained on the same domain.
And in that way,
it enables the fact
of comparing models with respect
to that specific capability.
So what the paper
tries to convey here
is that if you want to compare
models between each other,
you need to compare the training
mixture it has been trained on
and then ensure parity in terms
of training on the test task.
So you need to make sure that,
for example, the two have
been trained on the
test task or not.
And if it's one
and the other not,
then it might not be a
good thing to compare them.
It doesn't give you the
intrinsic value of the model.
So yeah, that's an
interesting phenomenon here.
Any questions?
OK.
Great.
So we can move on.
So one thing that I
was mentioning here
is that it's very hard to
get a sense of how good
a model is, even with
respect to benchmark scores,
because oftentimes what happens
is that as they come out,
people design data
on the training site
that resembles more what we try
to solve on the benchmark side.
So sometimes you end up
with models that score great
everywhere, but you as
a user don't necessarily
see added value to it.
And it's not the
fault of models.
It's not the fault
of the benchmarks.
It's just that it's very hard
to give a number that conveys
the value to you of the model.
So this is why people have
come up with other techniques
to put a number on
model evaluation.
And you might have
heard of Chatbots Arena.
Have any folks heard of it here?
Yeah.
So it's a website where
models can be submitted,
and users come in, and
they ask their questions,
and they're presented
responses from two models.
And they're being asked to
judge which one is better.
And then with some pairwise
computations done on the website
side, they come up with some
ranking in the end that ranks
model with respect to, quote
unquote, "user preference."
So it's a number
that is being put
on the vibes seen by the user.
And is it all perfect?
Actually, no.
So it suffers from
several issues that are--
another set of issues that
are hard to deal with.
So among them, when you have
a new model that comes in,
you have some noise at
the beginning with respect
to which other model it's
being compared against.
And these first few steps
actually influence quite a bit
the actual ranking, which
makes it a brittle property.
And there is a
paper that actually
shows that it's easily possible
to rig such a leaderboard.
So I'm not sure if there
is any evidence that it
has been done in the past.
But you can use
any model, if you
ask the question,
who are you, it's
just going to say who it is.
If you ask ChatGPT, who are you.
It's going to say,
hey, I'm ChatGPT,
I'm a helpful assistant.
And this paper observed on
this very simple property
that it was able to
detect what model
was being evaluated against.
And let's say, you have
an adversarial player,
it could rig the ranking just
by selecting the right model.
So it's not foolproof.
And then on other
aspects, so some
of the benchmarks that
evaluate these models,
they're actually
curated by experts
that know very well about the
target distribution of what
a given prompt should give.
So it has a set of guidelines
that says clearly, OK, this
is factual.
This is non-factual.
So they're able to determine
what is good versus bad.
And you as a user, you
might not know about it.
Because let's just take the
example of the teddy bear
that you wanted to
put in the washer,
if I don't know that I need
to hand wash my teddy bear,
and if I have a detailed
response regarding
you need to wash it with
a machine wash cold,
and I could, as a user,
find these pieces of advice
helpful because they
are actionable to me.
But actually, are they factual?
That is a whole other set
of issues that you as a user
wouldn't be able to tell
on a lot of queries.
And another challenge that we
have here is a user preference.
So who here likes it when there
are emojis in LLM responses?
Yes?
No?
Yeah.
Personally, I do.
And I think there
are strong opinions.
And some people
don't like it at all.
So they will down
rank such responses.
But actually, it's something
that the user should
be able to tell and choose.
And then the
distribution of people
who choose the best
model with respect
to the distribution of
the wider population that
is going to use
these models is going
to be different oftentimes.
And I think the emoji
case is a good example,
because I think
generally, emojis
are popular in the
wider population.
But I think domain experts
might not like it as much.
So I think that mismatch is
one that you would see here.
And then the last one I will
mention here is the safety side.
So you as a user,
you don't really
like it when a model
rejects your prompts.
When you ask about something,
and it says, OK, hey, sorry,
I cannot answer it.
So there will be a bias towards
responses that actually respond
to your query, rather than
respect some safety principle
that might be eventually the
intended product decision.
So there is also this kind
of bias that pops up here.
And as I was mentioning,
evaluation is a hard problem.
So you have all these
angles that you can explore.
And it's not one number
that's going to tell you
what you care about.
It's the combination
of all of these.
And in the end, it's tailored
to what you actually need.
So you would need to see
the strengths and weaknesses
of a given model and to
determine which one corresponds
to your use case.
So I'm going to come back to one
question about alignment here.
So we're going to see at the
next lecture a further step
into aligning the
model to do what
you want to do in a step
called preference tuning.
And then the combination of fine
tuning and preference tuning,
which comes after
pre-training, is what
we call alignment of the model.
So these two steps
are called alignments.
And I want to call
out one other thing.
There is one step we
didn't mention here
that is called mid training
that has been emerging
very recently, which
consists in a step
just after pre-training in
aligning the kind of data
that the model is being
trained on to the tasks
that you really care about.
So it's the same
pre-training objective
but aligning the kind of tasks
and the kind of data sets
to something that
you care about.
And yeah, so it's
an emerging trend.
I have not mentioned it,
but just so that you know,
mid training is
something that you
would have between
pre-training and fine tuning.
All good?
OK.
Great.
So now, we're going to tackle
one aspect of the challenges
that we had mentioned
regarding fine tuning, which
is computational expense--
the fact of being
computationally expensive.
And we're going to look at it
with one well-known technique
called LoRA, which
is a technique
to fine tune your weights
at the fine tuning stage
in an efficient manner.
So it's widely used.
And it saves a lot of compute.
So when you look at
your weight matrices,
instead of directly fine
tuning the whole weight matrix,
the LoRA technique
decomposes the fine tuning
between the weights of
the pre-trained model
and additional weights that
it decomposes into a low rank
multiplication.
So in this formulation,
the pre-trained weights
that you have is frozen.
So this W0 is frozen.
And then B and A are the
matrices that you need to tune.
So B and A are typically--
so they have dimensions that
will match the number of rows
and number of
columns respectively
for the number of rows of B
and number of columns of A.
But then the dimension of the
columns of B and then rows of A
is R, which is the rank of these
matrices, which is typically
taken very small.
So the dimensions of W is
typically hundreds or thousands,
and the dimension of R is
typically up to 10 or O of 10.
So as you can imagine, it
results in much less weights
to train.
And then I will mention
just other techniques
to improve efficiency and
then ease the fine tuning,
some methods called a
prefix tuning and adapters.
So they're explained
in the class textbook.
But we're not going to dive
deep into them because they're
less commonly used.
But just so that you know.
So let's walk through in
detail how does LoRA work.
So when you want to
fine tune your model,
so you have all
these ways for which
you have already
learned a distribution
at pre-training time.
So one naive way of
operating fine tuning
would be to directly
iterate on these weights.
But what we're doing
here, as we said,
is to decompose these into the
weights that we have already
pre-trained on and this
product of matrices.
And what LoRA says is that
you can do a forward pass
on both these
terms and then adds
these quantities in the end.
And A and B is going to
be a characterization
of your task of interest.
So let's say you
have a model that--
so Afshin was mentioning
the kinds of tasks
that you can maybe specialize
your model on, for example,
spam detection.
So you would take your
pre-trained model,
instantiate this B
and A in weights,
in the weights of your
model, fine tune on them.
And then what you will
have is that B and A
are going to be specific to
this task of spam detection,
similarly for sentiment
extraction and so on.
So it's a very nice
property that you
can start from a base model,
further tune your weights,
and then have your A's and
B's that are task specific.
So I want to comment
now on where were
these matrices being learned.
So in the original
paper of LoRA,
it mentioned training only
on the attention matrices.
But later on, people
realized that it might not
be the place where
it has the most
positive impact on performance.
And then there is a blog
that came out a few weeks ago
that studies this into
detail, and then they
realized that the feed-forward
blocks are actually
those where putting
LoRA is most beneficial.
So today, typically, both these
components carry LoRA matrices,
but the bulk of the
performance improvements
is actually contained in
the feed-forward block.
And then I want to mention
two interesting properties
about LoRA.
So when you fine tune
with LoRA weights,
you want to use a
higher learning rate.
So typically, 10 times
more is the guidance.
And then one interesting
fact is that it
doesn't perform as well when you
train it with larger batch size.
So I don't have a good
theoretical explanation
to give you for each of them.
It's more empirical observations
that have been emitted.
But to give the main lines
behind the mindset shared
from people who study
this phenomenon,
the first one might be guided
by the rank of the LoRA matrices
that might be small.
And as a result, given
the regions of space
that it needs to explore, you
need a higher learning rate.
And then the second
one, the hypothesis
here is that the training
dynamic of products of matrices
is different than a full matrix.
And this is where the increasing
batch size phenomenon occurs.
So it's basically
the explanations,
tentative explanations
given there.
So now, we're going to explore
an optimization of this.
But before I dive
deep into that part,
does anyone have any
questions on the LoRA part?
Yep.
Great point.
So the question is, do you
do grid search on the rank?
So you could.
So it's a design choice
to rank R. Typically,
people would have
done it before you.
So you have an idea of what
rank could be well suited
for your use case.
So you could definitely
do grid search,
or you could just
pick a popular value.
I think a 4 is used commonly.
You can just go
with one of them.
Yeah.
And we are going to see
that the reduction in number
of parameters is so huge
already that reducing even more
maybe doesn't matter that much.
That initial reduction by orders
of magnitude goes a long way,
and that is just a
hyperparameter tuning.
And you can see a
given rank in a given
setup as being a design choice.
So we have two
minutes, and we're
going to quickly
cover quantized LoRA.
So the techniques
that Afshin mentioned
just now regarding
quantizing weights
and so reducing the
memory footprint
is something that we're
going to see just here.
So when you look at these
matrices W0 and A and B,
what people have
done in this paper
is to quantize the weights of W0
into a format that is very smart
and then compute and
iterate on these matrices
that are being learned, A and
B in full precision, which
is in that case BF16.
And then the quantization
of these frozen weights
is super smart.
It's in a format
called NF4, which
assumes that the weights
are distributed normally.
And it splits the space into
quantiles rather than buckets
of fixed size, which puts
about the same amount of number
of values into each.
So it optimizes the bits
that you use for encoding.
And what it does is that it does
a double quantization process.
So it quantizes the weights.
And then in a second
step, it quantizes
the quantization constants that
we didn't see at length here.
But basically, when you want
to convert your full weights in
and out of quantized
states, you have
constants that are generated.
And they propose to quantize
these constants as well.
So this method generated
minus 16X VRAM savings,
and then the double quantization
methods gave some extra savings
but not that much.
But it's interesting to know.
And then we are exactly on time.
Thank you for your time.